Marion E. Dodd Papers, 1895-1969
Smith College Archives
Marion Elza Dodd Papers
1895-1969
Dodd, Marion E.
RG 80. Class of 1906.
4 boxes (1.5 linear ft.)
Smith College Archives Northampton, MA
Alumnae, founder of the Hampshire Book Shop, writer, Professor, History and Art of the Book. Contains biographical materials, photographs, correspondence, documents related to the Hampshire Bookshop (predecessor to the Grecourt Bookstore), and writings.
Biographical Note
Marion Elza Dodd was born in 1883 in Glen Ridge, NJ, to Charles T. and Rebecca Northall Dodd. Her grandfather, Moses Dodd, was the founder of Dodd, Mead Publishing Co., and many uncles and cousins were also book collectors, editors, and publishers. She received a B.A. from Smith College in 1906 and attended Columbia University Library School from 1908-1909. Dodd then co-founded the Hampshire Bookshop (the predecessor to the Grecourt Bookstore) with Mary Byers (Smith '08) on April 7, 1916. She also co-founded the National Association of College Bookstores in 1923 and became the first woman to receive an honorable fellowship of the American Booksellers Association in 1925. Dodd was a member of the Executive Board of American Booksellers' Association for 25 years, where she was the first woman officer. She served as secretary, and was the third Vice President. While living in Northampton, Massachusetts with Esther Dunn, Dodd published under the Hampshire Bookshop, and wrote prefaces, book reviews, and articles for publications such as Yankee Magazine, Publisher's Weekly, and Atlantic Monthly. She also taught a course in bookselling at Columbia University Library School during the summers of 1930-1931, and for four years taught a course for Smith College at the Hampshire Bookshop on the History and Art of the Book. She received an honorable M.A. from Smith College in 1936, and retired with honors as president and manager of Hampshire Bookshop in 1951, but served as Chairman of the Board there from 1951-1957. She died on March 16, 1961 in Northampton at the age of 78.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Marion Elza Dodd Papers cover 1895-1969 and contain biographical information, photographs, correspondence, publications, notes, catalogs, and publicity material. Of particular extent and interest are two sections: Hampshire Bookshop and Book Lover's Trail of New England. Hampshire Bookshop materials include store catalogs, fliers, newspaper advertisement clippings, and notes from store meetings. Items related to The Book Lover's Trail of New England, a series of articles written by Dodd about local authors, include most, if not all, of her research materials for each article. Here researchers can find detailed information, organized by state, on numerous local New England authors who wrote in the early 20th century.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the College Archives.
History of the Collection
The materials were donated over a period of time by Marion E. Dodd 1906 and acquired after her death by Smith College Archivist, Margaret Storrs Grierson 1922.
Search Terms
Dodd, Marion E., d. 1961.; Smith College--Students.; Hampshire Bookshop.; Booksellers and bookselling--Massachusetts--Northampton.; Bookstores--Massachusetts--Northampton.
Additional Information
Related Material
80. Class of 1906 Records
- Marion Elza Dodd - Biographical 1906-61 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Marion Elza Dodd - Photographs 1895-1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Corr. From Harold Nicolson 1934-36, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Corr. to Gordon Potter 1940-60 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Corr. from Vita Sackville-West (Vita Nicolson?) 1933-39 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Hampshire Bookshop 1921-51, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Publicity 1941-48 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs 1916-46, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Book Cartoons 1938, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Publicity, Book lists 1936-69, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Publicity, Book lists, Christmas lists, Staff 1924-51, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Book Lover's Trail of New England 1900-37 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Book Lover's Trail of New England 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Book Lover's Trail of New England 1939 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Book Lover's Trail of New England - Discarded Material 1939 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Yankee Magazine Articles - Along New England's Book Trails 1938-39 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Connecticut 1926-39 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Maine 1936-38 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Maine Miscellaneous 1938 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Connecticut Yankee - Maine article 1938 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- General Massachusetts 1938-39 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Maine Miscellaneous n.d. (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Massachusetts Authors 1937-38 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- New Hampshire 1938 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Rhode Island 1935-38 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Vermont 1937-38 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous 1910-46 (Box 4, Folder 4)